M Ganesh Kumar

Webpage: https://mgkumar138.github.io/ GitHub: https://mgkumar138.github.io/ GitHub: https://github.com/mgkumar138 LinkedIn: <a href="https://github.c

Summary

My interest is to understand how we learn world models to solve new problems quickly and when these models fail. My PhD work has been to develop biologically plausible spatial navigation reinforcement learning models to replicate one-shot learning behavior seen in animals. Prior to my PhD, I worked with human EEG and macaque spike data to develop Human-Computer Interfaces for wheelchair control. Currently, I am involved in computer vision projects for visual reasoning. My long-term goal is to extend my research in theoretical neuroscience to develop assistive technology that can alleviate learning disabilities posed by mental disorders.

Education

National University of Singapore

November 2022

- Ph.D. Computational Neuroscience
- Doctoral thesis: Biologically plausible computations underlying one-shot learning of paired associations
- Co-Advisors: Dr Andrew Tan (Physiolgy), Dr Yen Shih-Cheng (Engineering)
- Integrative Science and Engineering Programme (ISEP), NUS Graduate School (NGS)
- Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

National Institute of Education, Nanyang Technological University

April 2021

- M.Sc. Early Childhood Education
- Student exchange programme

Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)

August 2019

- Summer school 2019: Center for Brains, Minds & Machines (CBMM)
- Project: Compositional Models for Adaptive Learning in Vision

National University of Singapore

July 2017

- B.Sc. with Honors (Distinction) Life Sciences (Biomedical Sciences)
- University Scholars Programme (USP)
- Special Programme in Science (SPS)
- Honors thesis: Wheelchair control using motor-imagery based Electroencephalogram (EEG)

Research Experience

2022 – Present	Research Scientist I, Center for Frontier Al Research (CFAR), A*STAR
2017 – 2018	Research Engineer, A*STAR Artificial Intelligence Initiative (A*AI), A*STAR
Summer 2016	Intern, Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR
Summer 2013	Intern, Environmental Health Institute, National Environmental Agency (NEA)
Fall 2013	Intern, Ministry of Education (MOE)

Awards

- Fujitsu Laboratories MIT's Center for Brains, Minds and Machines Fellow 2019
- Al Singapore Summer school 2019 Best Poster
- NUS Graduate School Scholarship (NGSS) 2018 for Ph.D.
- NUSS Gold Medal for Outstanding Achievement 2017 (Best overall student in cohort for B.Sc.)
- University Scholars Programme (USP) Senior Honor Roll 2017 (Top 10%)
- A*STAR Undergraduate Scholarship (AUS) 2013 for B.Sc.
- SINDA Excellence Awards (JC) 2013 Top 10% Singapore Indian tertiary student

Publications

- <u>M Ganesh Kumar</u>, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong-Yi (2022). One-shot learning of paired association navigation using schemas and reward-modulated Hebbian plasticity. *In preparation*.
- M Ganesh Kumar, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong-Yi (2022). A nonlinear hidden layer enables actor-critic agents to learn multiple paired association navigation. *Cerebral Cortex*. https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhab456 [GitHub]
- M Ganesh Kumar, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong-Yi (2021). One-shot learning of paired associations by a reservoir computing model with Hebbian plasticity. arXiv preprint arXiv:2106.03580. https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.03580 [GitHub]
- M Ganesh Kumar, Kai Keng Ang, Rosa Q. So. (2017). Reject Option to reduce False Detection Rates for EEG-Motor Imagery based BCI. In Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society, EMBC 2017. 39th Annual International Conference of the IEEE. https://doi.org/10.1109/EMBC.2017.8037479

Invited talks

Dec 2022	Society for Neuroscience, Singapore symposium
Nov 2022	Senseable Intelligence group, MIT
Oct 2022	Metaconscious group, MIT
Sep 2022	Department of Computational Neuroscience, Max Planck Institute for Biological Cybernetics
Jun 2022	Three-minute thesis, Department of Physiology, NUS
Feb 2022	Biolins group, Brain and Cognitive Science department, MIT
Sep 2021	Neurobiology seminar, Life Science Institute, NUS

Conference posters

<u>M Ganesh Kumar</u>, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. One-shot learning of paired associations by a reservoir computing model with Hebbian plasticity. *Computational and Systems Neuroscience (COSYNE) Abstracts* 2022, Lisbon, Portugal.

<u>M Ganesh Kumar</u>, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. Learning working memory using a reservoir computing model trained by Hebbian plasticity for one-shot navigation to single displaced targets. *Neuroscience to Artificially intelligent systems (NAISys) 2022*, Virtual.

M Ganesh Kumar, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. One-shot learning of paired associations by a reservoir computing model with Hebbian plasticity. *Neuroscience 2021, Society for Neuroscience (SfN)*, Virtual.

<u>M Ganesh Kumar</u>, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. Learning multiple paired associations with temporal difference error modulated Hebbian plasticity. *Neuroscience to Artificially intelligent systems (NAISys) 2020*, Virtual.

<u>M Ganesh Kumar</u>, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. Learning multiple cuereward location associations using reservoir computing model & temporal difference error modulated Hebbian plasticity. *Neuromatch 2020*, Virtual.

M Ganesh Kumar, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. Liquid State Machine acquisition of paired associations with reward modulated Hebbian learning. **Bernstein Conference 2019**, Berlin, Germany.

Ad hoc Reviewer

Journals IEEE Transactions on Cognitive and Developmental Systems

Teaching

Jun 2022 STEP NUS Braincamp 2022

Oct 2021 NUS CET Beginning Artificial intelligence through Neuroscience

Jun 2021 Neuroscience, AI & Medicine workshop

Jun 2019 NUS Braincamp 2019

Jan 2019 – Dec 2019 LSM4213: Systems Neurobiology

Mentoring

Sep 2022 – Dec 2022 Clarence Sheng, A*STAR Internship Aug 2021 – Apr 2022 Xi Zhi Low, NUS Honors Project May 2020 – Apr 2021 Franklin Leong, NUS Honors Project

Jan 2019 – Apr 2020 Graduate research mentor, Special Programme in Science

Besides research

May 2019 – Present Co-founder & Data scientist Nugen.ai

Feb 2011 – Present Operations staff officer, Company Commander, Platoon Commander

Aug 2014 – Present Advisory Panel, President NUS Tamil Language Society

Tamil Al Companying

Jan 2019 – Dec 2019 Chairman Tamil+Al Symposium

- Motorcycle touring. I love to ride and have toured South East Asia.
- Crossfit. My wife convinced me that crossfit is fun.
- Theatre productions. I have produced, directed, and acted in student theatre productions.